Finding Aid for Victor Begg papers, 1973-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Victor Begg papers 1973-2010, 1990-2009
Begg, Victor.
(in 3 boxes)
1.6 linear feet
2011075 Aa 2
Collection of records, correspondence, memoranda, issued official statements, and architectural drawings of The Muslim Unity Center of Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, the Council of Islamic Organizations of Michigan and other Islamic organizations in Michigan and the U.S.; correspondence and memoranda, statements and articles written by and about interfaith organizations and projects in Michigan; also correspondence, conference presentations, speeches, and newspaper articles written by and about Victor Begg; reports and articles about Muslim communities in Michigan and in the U.S., politics in the Middle East, interfaith dialogue, and terrorism.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Victor Begg (donor no. 10551 ) in May 2011.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Victor (Ghalib) Begg is a retired businessman, senior advisor, chairman emeritus, and co-founder of the Council of Islamic Organizations of Michigan. He is also co-founder of the Muslim Unity Center Mosque in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, board member and co-founder of the Interfaith Leadership Council of Metropolitan Detroit, board member of the Michigan Round Table for Diversity and Inclusion, member of the Midwest Muslim-Catholic dialogue, and a frequent op-ed writer in the Detroit newspapers on Muslim issues. Begg has made numerous radio and TV appearances talking about Islam and issues faced by the Muslim community. In 2001 Begg was elected to the Bloomfield Hills Board of Education and served a four year term.
The Muslim Unity Center (MUC) in Bloomfield Hills, Mich. is a non-profit, Islamic organization dedicated to development, support and promotion of an Islamic way of life and the emergence of an American Muslim identity. MUC provides services and programs for the Muslim community of greater Detroit.
Council of Islamic Organizations of Michigan (CIOM) was established in 1993 with the goal of better addressing concerns of the Michigan Muslim community members, and unification of the ethnically and spiritually diverse Michigan Muslim community.
The Victor Begg collection, arranged into four series, documents the work of Victor Begg, as well as history, life and concerns of Michigan's Muslim community, and activities of Michigan and regional Islamic, Christian, Jewish, and interfaith organizations to promote religious and ethnic tolerance, and peace in the Middle East and other regions. A large portion of collection documents the history of the Muslim Unity Center in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan. Interfaith cooperation and the image of the American Muslim community in light of the September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks and other terrorist acts are central themes of the collection.
Subjects:
Begg, Victor.; Arab Americans--Michigan.; East Indian Americans--Michigan.; Interfaith worship.; Islam--United States.; Muslim Unity Center (Bloomfield Hills, Mich.); Muslims--Religious life--Michigan.; Muslims--Social life and customs--Michigan.; Muslims--United States.; Religious institutions--Michigan.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Terrorism.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.
- Victor Begg papers
  The Victor Begg series contains letters received by Victor Begg from religious and political leaders, as well as members of Muslim community. Correspondence includes letters from viewers of Begg's TV program about Islam, letters from Michigan and U.S. political leaders, leaders of Islamic, Christian, Jewish, and interfaith organizations, as well as elementary school children. The series also includes a handful of personal documents, materials related to Begg's Bloomfield Hills Board of Education campaign, and photographs taken during interfaith conferences and meetings with Michigan and U.S. political leaders.
  - Personal 1973, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1989-2000s (scattered), undated (Box 1)
  - Bloomfield Hills Schools 2001 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings 1990s-2000s (scattered) (Box 1)
    (see also articles written by and about Victor Begg and his work in box 3)
  - Photographs 1990s, undated (Box 1)
  - Cassette tape (Box 1)
    (interview with Victor Begg conducted by Sally Howell)
- Islamic organizations
  The Islamic organizations series contains correspondence, memoranda, statements and newspaper clippings of articles by and about a number of Michigan-based and national Islamic organizations. Much of correspondence, memoranda and other documentation in the series belongs to Victor Begg. Among organizations represented are the American Society for Religious and Cultural Understanding (ASRU), American Muslim Council (AMC), Council of Islamic Organizations of Michigan (CIOM), Muslim-American Alliance, The Islamic Society of North American, and several others. The Muslim Unity Center files shed light on the MUC history and activities. Also included are drafts of MUC constitution, by-laws and policies, Board of Trustees meetings agenda and minutes, correspondence and memoranda, financial reports and budget, and select building documentation (descriptions and plans).
  - American Society for Religious and Cultural Understanding 1988-1991 (Box 1)
  - American Muslim Council 1990-1991, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Council of Islamic Organizations of Michigan 1990-2010, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Muslim-American Alliance 1993-1995, undated (Box 1)
  - The Muslim Unity Center
    - Constitution 1999-2000, undated (Box 1)
    - By-laws 2002, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous policies 2001-2004 (with gaps), undated (Box 1)
    - Meetings agenda and minutes 1993, 1997, 1999-2004, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and memoranda 1993-1994, 1999-2003, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Finances 1993, 1996, 2000-2004, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - The building 1993-2002 (with gaps) and undated (Box 1)
    - "The community journal," January 2006 and summer 2010 (Box 1)
    - Plans, drawings and related material 1990s (Box 3)
  - The Islamic Society of North American 2002-2010 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous organizations 1996-2010 (scattered) (Box 1)
- Muslim community
  The Muslim community series contains correspondence, articles, and news clipping depicting social, economic, political, and religious life of Muslim community: the religion of Islam, political involvement, business life, education, traditions and customs, as well as position on international terrorism and image of the Muslim community in light of terrorist attacks at home and abroad.
  - Islam 1989-2009, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Politics and government 1990-2010 (scattered) and undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Muslims and terrorism 1989-2009 (scattered) and undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings 1988-2010 (scattered) and undated (Box 1)
    (see also oversize clippings in box 3)
- Interfaith dialogue
  The Interfaith dialogue series contains correspondence, memoranda, official statements, conference materials, articles, reports, and newspaper clippings on the subject of cooperation of different religious communities. Materials discuss religious and ethnic tolerance, economic development, peace in the Middle East, and views on terrorism.
  - Trialogue events 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Interfaith relations 2000-2010, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Interfaith Partners 2002-2006 (Box 2)
  - The Children of Abraham Project 2004-2005 (Box 2)
  - Jewish-Muslim relations 1993, 2000-2010 (with gaps), 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Midwest Catholic-Muslim Dialogue 2006-2007, 2010 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings 1990s-2000s (scattered) (Box 2)